Chapter 84.
Pitch polling.
To make them run easily and swiftly, the axles of carriages are anointed, and for
much the same purpose, some whalers perform an analogous operation upon
their boat. They grease the bottom. Nor is it to be doubted that as such a
procedure can do no harm, it may possibly be of no contemptable
advantage, considering that oil and water are hostile, that oil is a sliding
thing, and that the object in view is to make the boat slide bravely. Quiquang
believed strongly in anointing his boat, and one morning, not long after the
German ship Yungfra disappeared, took more than customary pains in that
occupation, crawling under its bottom, where he hung over the side, and rubbing
in the anxiousness as though diligently seeking to ensure a crop of hair from
the craft's bald keel. He seemed to be working in obedience to some particular presentiment,
nor did it remain unwarranted by the event. Towards noon, whales were raised,
but so soon as the ship sailed down to them, they turned and fled with swift precipited
flight as of Cleopatra's barges from Actium. Nevertheless, the boats pursued,
and Stubs was foremost. By great exertion, Tash Teego at last succeeded
in planting one iron, but the stricken whale, without at all sounding, still
continued his horizontal flight with added fleetness. Such unintermitted
strainings upon the planted iron must sooner or later inevitably extract it.
It became imperative to lance the flying whale, or be content to lose him. But to
haul the boat up to his flank was impossible. He swam so fast and furious.
what then remained.
Of all the wondrous devices and dexterities, the slights of hand, and
countless subtleties to which the veteran whaleman is so often forced,
none exceed that fine maneuver with the lance, called pitch pulling. Small sword
or broadsword, in all its exercises boasts nothing like it. It is only
indispensable with an ineterate running whale. Its grand fact and feature is the
wonderful distance to which the long lance is accurately darted from a
violently rocking jerking boat under extreme headway. Steel and wood
included. The entire spear is some 10 or 12 ft in length. The staff is much
slider than that of the harpoon and also of lighter material, pine. It is
furnished with a small rope called a warp of considerable length by which it
can be hauled back to the hand after darting.
But before going further, it is important to mention here that though
the harpoon may be pitch pulled in the same way with the lance, yet it is
seldom done, and when done, it is still less frequently successful on account of
the greater weight and inferior length of the harpoon as compared with the
lance, which in effect become serious drawbacks. As a general thing,
therefore, you must first get fast to a whale before any pitch pulling comes into play.
Look now at Stub, a man who, from his humorous, deliberate coolness and
equinimity in the dyest emergencies, was specially qualified to excel in pitch
pulling. Look at him. He stands upright in the tossed bow of the flying boat,
wrapped in fleecy foam. The towing whale is 40 ft ahead. Handling the long lance
lightly, glancing twice or thrice along its length to see if it be exactly
straight, Stub whistlingly gathers up the coil of the warp in one hand, so as
to secure its free end in his grasp, leaving the rest unobstructed.
Then, holding the lance full before his waistband's middle, he levels it at the
whale. When covering him with it, he steadily depresses the butt end in his
hand, thereby elevating the point till the weapon stands fairly balanced upon
his palm 15 ft in the air. He minds you somewhat of a juggler balancing a long
staff on his chin. Next moment, with a rapid, nameless impulse, in a superb,
lofty arch, the bright steel spans the foaming distance and quivers in the life
spot of the whale. Instead of sparkling water, he now spouts red blood.
That drove the spigot out of him, cried Stub. This July's immortal all fountains
must run wine today. Would now it were old New Orleans whiskey or old Ohio or
unspeakable old man Gahala? Then Tashego lad, I'd have you hold a can to the jet
and we'd drink round of it. Yay! Verily, hearts alive. Weed brew choice punch in
the spread of his spout hole there. From that live punch bowl qua the living stuff
again and again to such gamesome talk.
The dextrous dart is repeated, the spear returning to its master like a greyhound
held in skillful leash. The agonized whale goes into his flurry, the towel
line is slackened, and the pitchpuller dropping a stern folds his hands and
mutely watches the monster die.